<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The peaceable Christian A sermon.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56754</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832722</idno>
  <idno type="VID">37196</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240933520</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P923</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221412</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832722</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99832722e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56754)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37196)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2149:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The peaceable Christian A sermon.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6, 9-24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Tho. Snowden, for Tho. More, at the Maiden-Head over against St. Dunstans-Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprimatur (A1v) dated: June, 10. 1678.</note>
                  <note>Text and register are continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Christian life --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Zev Berger </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37196:1"/>
            <p>THE PEACEABLE CHRISTIAN. A SERMON.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Snowden,</hi> for <hi>Tho. More,</hi> at the <hi>Maiden-Head</hi> over against St. <hi>Dunstans-Church.</hi> 1678.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:37196:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Guil. Sill.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>June, 10. 1678.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37196:2"/>
            <head>THE PEACEABLE CHRISTIAN.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>ROM. 12. 18.</bibl>
               <q>If it be possible, and as much as lieth in you, live peaceably with all men.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN a World wherein so much evil is both done and suffered, wherein all mankind are both Agents and Patients in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon guilt; nothing is perhaps more difficult than to maintain moderate and peaceable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentments in the midst of such provocations as constantly surround us; a quiet, a forgiving frame of spirit, being not more necessary to the constitution of a good Christian, than it
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37196:3"/> is hard to be obtained by him. Yet he that belongs to Christ, ought to have his Soul above the common humours of passion and revenge; for as he has learned not to do evil to another, so also not to prosecute it too severely when done against himself. He has learned to shew more displeasure against his own faults, than against those of other men: And in short, is ready to be at peace with any offender, sooner than with his own guilty self. For though the World thinks it a commendable height of cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage not to give place to wrath; yet grace by a new method, riseth to a more solid great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; it overcomes provocations only by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving them, and conquers injuries by gentle and moderate returns, whilst instead of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting it self in contriving how to carry on any unchristian differences; it makes this rather the business of its holy endeavours, <hi>viz.</hi> That if it be possible, and as much as lieth in it, to live peaceably with all men. Our Apostle at the <hi>9th v.</hi> of this excellent Chapter, ingages into a discourse of brotherly love, in pursu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of which he exhorts the believing <hi>Romans</hi> to charity and hospitality towards their poorer brethren, <hi>v.</hi> 13. and thence proceeds to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vise them how to carry it towards an offending
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:37196:3"/> Brother also, <hi>viz.</hi> that they should bless their persecutors, and that they should not curse even the worst of men, <hi>v.</hi> 14. but that they should sympathize, and share both in the joys and griefs of all their fellow Christians, <hi>v.</hi> 15. that they should be humble in their own thoughts, and in their behaviour towards o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men, <hi>v.</hi> 16. being far from returning injury for injury, <hi>v.</hi> 17. but if it was possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and as much as lieth in them, that they should live peaceably with all men. For says he, <hi>If it be possible,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> If it be possible—Humane nature is so cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, and humane practices are so perverse, that to live altogether peaceably, is look'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the Holy <hi>Paul</hi> as a thing almost impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible; the unkindness of others showring so many injuries upon us, and our own proud hearts, flowing with such streams of bitterness, that the whole world may well be drowned under quarrels, and contentions; and in so universal a deluge, no wonder if the peaceful Dove can find no room to rest its foot amongst men so unkind in their deportment, and so haughty in their passions. Well might the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle question the very possibility of living peaceably; lest therefore that we should think
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37196:4"/> that to do absolutely so, is indeed impossible; we find him descending one degree nearer to humane capacity, if you think that to do this perfectly be impossible;</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Yet at least, as far as you are able, and asmuch as lieth in you <hi>live, &amp;c.</hi> For 'tis true, we cannot force the will of our neighbour, it is not in our power to bend his stubborn Soul, to bow his stiff and lofty neck, or to lame his savageness into a more sociable disposition. But though he is not in our power, yet we our selves are: a wise man has command over himself, has power to humble his own pride, to cool his own passions, to chain up his anger, and revenge those wild beasts; which when loose are apt to fly at all; and if we will but keep those poysonous Serpents out of it, we may maintain a paradise in our own bosoms; we may be quiet in the midst of a provoking world. So that if men would but preserve peaceableness in their own proper actions, it would lessen every dissention, by crushing the ill humours whilst in the egg, and by rebating at least the point of the keenest malice; and this would prove one step towards living pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceably with other men.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Peaceably, says the Apostle, and in that word
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37196:4"/> he commends to us a grace not only going far to the making of a true Christian, but to the making of him happy also. Peace, and good will being those great Blessings, promised by the Angels that proclaimed the birth of our ever blessed Jesus, <hi>Luke</hi> 2. 14. The dearest Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy bequeathed to his Disciples by their dying Lord, <hi>John</hi> 14. 27. Peace is one of those at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes which adorn the Crown of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, who is pleased to be stiled the God of Peace; as <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 33. &amp; 16. 20. In a word, it's one of those blessed circumstances by which his heavenly Kingdom is commended to us. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 13. This is that grace so often called for by our Apostle, as that Christians should be at peace amongst themselves, 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 5. 13. And that they should follow peace with all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men too, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 14. With all men, being the last circumstance considerable in the Text. Our goodness ought to extend to all mankind, we should live peaceably with all; shewing it by patience towards all, 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 5. 14. By doing good to all, <hi>v.</hi> 15. By being gentle unto all, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 24. and in fine, by shewing all meekness to all men, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 2. With all, then is the great extent of this duty, especially with the houshold of faith, with those that are shut
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37196:5"/> up in the same inclosure of the Christian Church: but though these have the first title to this peace, yet ought it not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to all the common world besides: Plainly to our goodness the good have a most unquestioned title, and yet even the worst of men should not be excluded from their share in it also. With all mankind, therefore it is our duty to be peaceable. Humane charity should be extended as far as humane nature; and a Christians peace be as universal, as catholick, as his religion: his meekness should be confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in no narrower bounds than those the world it self confesses. <hi>Live peaceably with all men,</hi> with our friends; for the contrary is unnatural, with our professed Enemies, since the contrary is unchristian: we should be quiet with the quiet, because that is but just, and with the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet too, because that becomes, our credit and repose: with all, because we owe a duty to all. And thus I have both explained the words in all their parts, and at the same time, I hope suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently proved the duty too, from those several parallel Texts already cited.</p>
            <p>That therefore, to live peaceably, to be of<note place="margin">Doct.</note> an universally calm, mild, and forgiving dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, is the character of every true Christian.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37196:5"/> I shall take for granted, and confine my self at present only to examine the duty in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of the text adding both motives and directions necessary to its performance: we should be peaceable: 1. With all: 2. With all as far as it is possible: 3. With all as much as in us lies. But I shall wave this method, and consider the true extent of the duty, before I prosecute the duty it self, which in the Text has a double limitation: 1. As far as it is pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, and 2. as much as in us lies. And now that I may impose a distinct sense upon both those expressions which, may probably seem to carry the same, I shall take leave to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand the possibility, only for those things that are in our power; and then as much as in us lies, for the things that are lawful, and indeed when we consider that a good man can be rightly said to be able to do only those things that he can lawfully do, perhaps the exposition will not seem very much forced. 1. Then as far as it is possible the Gospel obliges us not to<note place="margin">Limitation</note> act impossibilities; but in all possible occasions we must keep the Christian Peace. We live<note place="margin">Luk. 17. 1.</note> in an age wherein it is not morally possible to avoid all occasions of offence, we do often such things that others may take in evil part; but
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37196:6"/> these things we must labour with all diligence to avoid, briefly it is possible, either not to do ill at all to any one, or at least not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it when done; not to justify what possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly we could not avoid.</p>
            <p>If therefore out of infirmity of nature, or surprise of the temptaion, we at any time fail in our duties, let us not double our sin, by defending, by prolonging it; nor go on by the continuance of our differences, to shew that we delight in them. If it was not possible to avoid the beginning of quarrels, it is I hope yet pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible to make an end of them; and by the sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den taming of our unruly passions, make at least a kind of satisfaction to God and man, both of whom we had offended. Shortly, in all those differences abounding in a contentious world. I fear there are but few can be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved unavoidable in their beginnings, and I am sure there are none impossible to be concluded, did but both parties resolve to do their duties. Let us therefore know that our power goes farther than we are willing to grant it, and that our duty, our peaceableness ought to go as far as our power: which I told you a good Christian will believe to be only as far as it is lawful, that being the <hi>2d.</hi> Limitation I set to<note place="margin">2. L.</note>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:37196:6"/> the duty of the Text. Honesty, what is just, and lawful, ought to be the great bound of our charity; for we are not to agree with all men upon any terms, to agree with any man in his sin; we ought not so much to study to be at peace with men, as to be at peace with their vices too, and consequently at enmity with God, and at open war with Heaven: we should in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed study to live like brethren, but not like <hi>Simeon,</hi> and <hi>Levy,</hi> brethren in iniquity. Briefly<note place="margin">Gen. 49. 6.</note> we ought to quarrel with nothing but sin: nay and there to have a care of being moved against the person, rather than the fault; to see that our zeal against offence, ingage us not to be unkind, uncharitable, or unnatural against the offender; for otherwise we may prosecute sin in a sinful manner. We must therefore, if religion will allow it, be peaceable with all men, be kind, and good natured, as far as we can be so with a good conscience; and I know that very few of our quarrels can be excuse upon a religious, or consciencious pretence; till therefore we find that Christ suffers as well as we, we should labour to live peaceably with all men. The truth of which in both its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents is sufficiently proved by the places foreci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, all with all, and towards all, being the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37196:7"/> constant additions to this duty. 1. With our relations according to the flesh, with those friends of ours that are the dear parts of our selves, how unnatural would all disagreement be with them? we find how severely the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle speaks of such as fail in their duties to their own house, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 8. Nay Hell it self is not divided within it self, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. 26. and certainly such would be thought brutish, and distracted who wound their own bodies, tear their ovvn flesh, and love to be letting forth their ovvn blood; and yet this does every man vvho treats his friends vvith injuries, and despite. <hi>2ly,</hi> vve should extend our goodness to strangers too, for some by so doing have entertained Angels, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 2. At least how know we but they may be particular Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Jesus Christ. Let us therefore be kind and peaceable with all persons how little soever we are concerned with them, and that whether they be good; or whether they be bad for the good; he that quarrels with them is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Devils Champion, a persecutor of virtue, an Enemy of innocence, and a man so desperately wicked, that it cannot be hoped the short limits of such a discourse should be powerful enough to reclaim him, neither in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37196:7"/> was it designed to such. Therefore,</p>
            <p>2. We should, as far as it is lawful, be at peace with those that either are, or we suppose to be bad: for all are not really evil whom we please to think so: with the worst men we should be as peaceable as innocently we may, and with these is indeed the greatest exercise of of a Christian's vertue, and therefore to these I shall limit the following part of my dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, as affording the most difficult part of our duty: For if we love only those that love us, what thanks have we? do not sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, that is, the vilest of men the same? <hi>Luke</hi> 6. 33. But now to love our enemies, to do good where there neither has been any foregoing obligation, and from whence in likelihood can be expected no return: To do good for evil, and to answer injuries with acts of charity, and kindness; this is an exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of a Christians virtue, and a triumph of that goodness which becomes the followers of the Prince of Peace: Patience towards the froward, forgiveness towards the offending Brother, and, in some, peaceableness with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and enemies that provoke us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stanly; these are both a Christians duty, and his honour; and to the doing of this he may be moved.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:37196:8"/>
            <p>First, If he consider how pleasing this must<note place="margin">1 Mot.</note> needs be to our good and merciful God, to him who doubtlesly looks down from the Throne of his Holiness, with pleasure and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction upon those who are thus far like himself; for he does good in general to all; he causes his Sun to rise upon the just and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>just, <hi>Luke</hi> 6. 35. He distributes the common blessings of humane life to all indifferently, to his rebels, as well as to his faithful subjects; he is not quick to strike, though he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly provoked to it; he revenges not every unkindness with a dreadful quarrel; he silen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces not the noise of every oath with the louder voice of thunder, nor aims his deadly lightning at the head of every one that offends; should he do so, he would soon lay all nature waste, and fill the whole Earth with the dreadful marks of his displeasure: No! he forbears even the bad, and as thus to our comfort we know that he is peaceable; so for our example, we ought to know it too; and therefore we may be sure that he dislikes all that is so unlike himself, that he abhors those revenges which he never practises, that he hates nothing so much as those unchristian passions, those scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous resentments of malice and revenge
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37196:8"/> which fall so far short of his divine similitude, that they rather resemble the old Serpent; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and that pride from whence it springs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the poison with which he himself at first burst, and with which he still infects all his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers: but for those who pretend to be the followers of the Lamb of God: They should</p>
            <p n="2">2. Consider the great example of the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful<note place="margin">2 Mot.</note> Jesus; he that received all the ill which the wicked and provoking world was capable of laying upon him, and yet never returned any; but when he was reviled, he reviled not again; and suffered without threatning revenge, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 23. Nay, that died pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for his murtherers, <hi>Luke</hi> 23. 34. He there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that was so much a Lamb both in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence and meekness, will never own such as are Wolves and Tigers; amongst whom there is nothing to be heard but passionate howlings, nor to be seen but rending and tearing each other; whereas to bless those that curse; to love enemies, and to do good to those that hate us, are the principles he went upon, and which he commends to his true<note place="margin">Luk. 6. 27, 28.</note> Disciples.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This peaceableness will be to the honour<note place="margin">3 Mot.</note> of the Religion we profess; for alas, does not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37196:9"/> Christianity it self suffer through the miscarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages of its professors! Can that be thought a Gospel of Peace, whose followers delight in nothing but divisions? who will not bear one offence, nor receive one injury without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning it to the full; and it is well if not with interest too: Thus two ill natur'd proverbs are more observed by them, than all the precepts of the holy Gospel, whilst they resolve not to die in the debt of their ill willers, but to give to every one as good as he brings, but does this become Religion? are these haughty and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient maxims drawn out of the Word of God? is this to glorifie him? and this to adorn his Gospel of peace? as it is called, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 6. 15. by these passions we may perhaps become burning, but never shining lights, persons whom none can satisfie or touch, and whom none can safely imitate. But</p>
            <p n="4">4. By unmercifulness in our own practices, we forfeit our title to the Divine mercy, since we cannot with reason hope, that God should deal better with us, than we do with our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, who owe us incomparably less duty, and who affront us infinitely less than we do our God. In our prayers to him we are taught to make this the very condition of our pardon,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37196:9"/> namely, our aptitude to forgive a trespassing Brother, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. 12.</p>
            <p>Whilst therefore we our selves are unpeace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, we make our own forgiveness desperate by denying to forgive others.</p>
            <p n="5">5. This ill humour will be to our discredit<note place="margin">5 Mot.</note> as well as to our damage; for there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation like that of being wise and good: but now what wisdom is there in exposing our passionate follies to the discourse of our tatling neighbour? or what goodness in being excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious? in being ready to quarrel upon every affront; those therefore will certainly practice this pacifick vertue, who stand upon their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit with the wise, or better part of the World; since such will look with respect and pity up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on afflicted patience, and will pay honour to goodness unmoved in the midst of persecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: whilst the noise of our passions will but awake the censure and reproof of the specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor World, which is apt to subscribe to the opinion of that wise Prince, who tells us, that anger resteth in the bosom of fools, <hi>Eccles.</hi> 7. 9. whereas it is the discretion of a man to defer his anger, and his glory, to pass over transgressions, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19. 11.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It is destructive to our inward peace; for<note place="margin">6 Mot.</note> alas, what quiet can there be within? when
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37196:10"/> there is no such noise, and so many disturbances without; a mind possessed with those furies of malice and revenge will find as little rest, as houses do when haunted with disturbing Ghosts; he that entertains these passions, had as good entertain so many Devils, and will find as much in their company; for he laies his soul upon the rack, and finds no rest till he has over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his enemy, or himself, and which of these is the nobler conquest, let every Christian judg.</p>
            <p n="7">7. This peaceful inclination will add to a<note place="margin">7 Mot.</note> man's outward quiet also, whereas the contrary shall ingage us in perpetual vexations: Since the quarrelsom shall never want some to quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel with, and the exceptions shall never want occasions; and with the froward the whole World learns frowardness. But if one party at least will resolve to be quiet, the difference can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not certainly be long liv'd: no malice can be so unreasonable as to fight on where it meets with no opposition; and the most violent fires will go out, and die, if you once withdraw their fuel; but on the other side, by disturbing our neighbour's peace, we disturb our own also, since it is almost impossible to keep our own temper whilst we are moving another man's.</p>
            <p n="8">8. This will leave our unreasonable enemies<note place="margin">Mot. 8.</note> without excuse: those who when we are for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37196:10"/> Peace do yet resolve upon War, as the Royal Psalmist complains of his, <hi>Psa.</hi> 120. 7. our peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableness will shew where the fault indeed lies, and by the same action we shall both acquit our selves, and condemn them.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Which is indeed a motive most Christian;<note place="margin">Mot. 9.</note> this is the likeliest to reclaim an offending Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for how know we but that by our peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, patient, and mild behaviour, we may shame our enemies out of all their malice; and by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so, we may of enemies make them both our servants, and God's too; and so an offending Brother (if you will pardon the expression) shall come to be saved by our mercy, in a sense as well God's, whilst our patience makes a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert of the persecutor, and disarms that malice which would have done infinitely more hurt to it self than to us. And oh the joy! the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian satisfaction! to see an enemy by our vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue changed into a friend, to see violence dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed only by our yielding to it. How great! nay how godlike a design it is, to do good to the undeserving, by the conversion of an enemy to dress up Trophies to the honour of our good nature; and to do at once both God and our selves good service; whilst by the efficacy of a good example, we not only overcome evil with<note place="margin">Rom. 12. 21</note> good, but we do it so as to make the evil good;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:37196:11"/> which is a work so properly belonging to God, that it must needs be a design worthy the nob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lest spirit, and becoming the most religious am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition.</p>
            <p n="10">10. By our giving place to wrath, we ingage<note place="margin">Mot. 10.</note> God in our quarrels; <hi>Vengeance is mine, and I will repay, saies the Lord, Rom.</hi> 12. 19. He will do it, but upon this condition, that we offer not at it our selves; for he may very well forbear to interest himself at all in those quarrels wherein we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest our selves too deeply; and if we prosecute every wrong with too much eagerness, he may justly leave us to our own perhaps impotent and feeble prosecutions▪ so that the unpeaceable will not give God leave to revenge those evils, which a thousand to one, but after all their fury they themselves will not be able to revenge; but if we could once resolve to trust God with our cause, then would be the time for his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed appearing in it.</p>
            <p>Lastly, The unpeaceable ought to know<note place="margin">Mot. 11.</note> that they have no enemies which are not of God's raising up; all that provokes us are but instruments in his Almighty hand; our greatest foes are but the Rods of his Justice, which <hi>David</hi> well considered, when he answered, <hi>It may be the Lord hath said unto Shimei, curse David, 2 Sam.</hi> 16. 10. Let us not therefore by our impatiency, like
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37196:11"/> mad Dogs, bite the stones that have been thrown at us; nor like rebellious children, fly at that Rod with which it pleased our Father to give us correction; but let us believe our worst ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to be God's executors; and therefore like humbled children, let us be ready even to kiss those Rods that made us smart: to forgive, and embrace those men God has made use of for our punishment; being assured of this, that if they mingle their own malice with his Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Justice, they themselves shall be called to as severe an account, when God like an indulgent Father may come to break that stick with which he beat us, and to burn those Rods with which he had corrected his repenting, weeping chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. As therefore we expect God should own<note place="margin">Exhort.</note> our Couse, let us be exhorted to patience, chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and forgiveness, even under the greatest pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations: To the doing of which I shall add these following Directions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Those who would live peaceably, ought<note place="margin">Direct. 1.</note> carefully to avoid the giving of all just offence; they ought to make conscience of provoking one another, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 26. for to hope for peace where we allow provocations, is too unreason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Upon any offence offered to us, we must bridle the first motions of our anger, and curb
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:37196:12"/> the first heat of our words. We must not harden our hearts, nor whet our tongues like sharp swords, as <hi>David</hi> words it of his enemies; for<note place="margin">Psal. 64. 3.</note> indeed it's no wonder if fire be produc'd by the collision of an Iron tongue, and flinty heart; sharp words, and obstinate minds, being enough to put whole Societies into a flame.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. We should not stand upon too nice points,nor ingage into disputes upon every slight occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion; for certainly that part is not very sound, which seems so tender as not to indure the slightest touch.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. (For I can but name them) let us put fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourableconstructions upon doubtful and sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picious passages; for all is not evil that at first appears to be so; and it's no sign of good na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to take every thing in the worst sense.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 5. We should be willing to debate calmly,and to discourse over those things cooly, which look like injuries; misunderstanding being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly one of the greatest make-bates; those therefore that keep at an unkind distance, do prevent all opportunities of reconcilement.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 6. Let every ones ears be stopped againstthe tale-bearer. Informers generally in every quarrel playing the Devil's game for him, and blowing up the flame on both sides. They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing such whisperers that separate very friends, <hi>Prov.</hi> 17. 9.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:37196:12"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 7. Use all holy endeavours to reclaim thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juriousBrother; conquer him by soft and gentle remonstrances, by friendly concessions rather than by a greater and more furious passion.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 8. Resolve to pardon even the most resolved of thy enemies; the worse they are, do thou still labour to appear the better, and make the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess of their ill, only an occasion of heightening thy our vertue.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> 9. And with which I shall conclude, Shewthy peaceful disposition by endeavouring peace amongst all other men; by promoting charity and love between all dissenting Christians; to reconcile, to act the Mediatour, is a holy, and a Gospel work; a work that our dearest Saviour thought worthy of his blood and death: This is more charitable than to run with water when your neighbour's house is flaming; more chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table than to pull his child out of the fire into which it is fallen: See not therefore such unkind and such destructive flames, without casting in some charitable drops, some discreet advices, and some good Offices, that so others may find the benefit of thy goodness, and that brotherly love may on all hands continue. Briefly, let us all be perswaded to this duty, and that in the true extent of it. Let no provocations discom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37196:13"/> our graces; no injuries disturb the peace of our minds, or tempt us to disturb the peace of other men, and so by a patient, yielding temper▪ we shall blunt the malice, and disarm the fury of our eager enemies; and what is more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable? we shall gain God over to our side, and consequently hasten our deliverance: And thus by discharging our duty, we shall obtain peace at the hand of God; we shall increase peace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the Sons of men. In one word, we shall save our own souls, and be instrumental also to the salvation even of those men who would perhaps have undone us. Whilst by the reclaiming of such as injure us, by the convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our persecutors, we give them good cause to be our friends, who possibly have been our enemies, without any at all. This kind of converting an injurious Brother, is a doing of God's work, is the way to commend our own dear souls to the mercy and goodness of that God, who is pleased with all opportunities of reconcilement; and in fine, it is to present him with a wandering, a guilty servant, brought back by us unto his duty, at whose conversion Heaven it self will be filled with joy, and all the holy Angels sing.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:37196:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>